Waclaw Graczewski papers 1910-1925 CPAA 87-60
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Waclaw Graczewski papers
1910-1921
Graczewski, Waclaw
CPAA 87-60
1 box (0.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Waclaw Graczewski, a first generation immigrant from Poland, came to the U.S. at the turn of the century. He was active in many social organizations established by Polish immigrants in Thompsonville, Connecticut. The collection consists of constitutions, by-laws and dues paid to these organizations.
Historical/Biographical Note
Waclaw Graczewski, who also signed his last name as Grcewski, lived in Thompsonville, Connecticut. He was an active member of various Polish American social groups and clubs such as The Legion of Free Krakusy, The Polish-Roman-Catholic Brotherhood Saint Adalbert Society, and Thaddeus Kosciuszko Society. The collection contains constitutions, by-laws, loan and tax booklets from the various social groups. There are two of badges from two of the social groups - Legion of the Free Polish Krakusy, and the Thaddeus Kosciuszko Society.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection contains constitutions, by-laws, loan and tax booklets from the various social groups. There are two of badges from two of the social groups: Legion of the Free Polish Krakusy, and the Thaddeus Kosciuszko Society.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Mrs. Bertha Waleryszak, a daughter of Mr. Waclaw Graczewski, Enfield, Connecticut, 1987.
Search Terms
Waclaw Graczewski; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Immigrants -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Thompsonville.; Pamphlets.; Badges.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Mieczyslaw Kierklo papers CPAA 87-47
Czeslaw Gieniewski papers CPAA 08-09
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by date.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Waclaw Graczewski papers, information about donation and general description of donated items., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- By-laws and membership dues of the Legion of Free Polish Krakusy., 1917-1919 and 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Waclaw Graczewski's tax record booklet for St. Adalbert Society., 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Parish book of St. Adalbert's church, Thompsonville, owned by Maria Juszkiewicz., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Pamietnik (Souvenir of Polish Government Loan) in memory of donors, published by A. Wasilewski, Springfield, Mass., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- By-laws of the Polish-Roman-Catholic brotherhood of St. Adalbert Society, 1925; supplement to constitution, Dec. 1937., 1925, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- By-laws and donations of the Legion of Free Polish Krakusy under the Protection of St. Stanislaus, published 1920, dues recorded 1934-1953. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Kosciuszko Junior High School plaque dedication and banquet, booklet, Enfield Conn., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Constitution and donations of the Free Polish Krakusy, dues recorded for 1932, 1954-1959; supplement to constitution, July 2, 1933. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Constitution and by-laws of the Thaddeus Kosciuszko Society, 1921; amendments to the constitution, March 12, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Two badges: Legion of the Free Polish Krakusy - 1904 and Thaddeus Kosciuszko Society badge - 1921. (Box 1, Folder 11)